Register of the World War I subject collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Newspapers and clippings, 1914, 1918 (Box-folder 18: 25)
  Includes: special editions of the Berliner Lokal-Anzeiger, the Berliner Tageblatt und Handels-Zeitung, and the Neue Zeit Charlottenburger Zeitung (February - October 1918); an edition of the Frankfurter Zeitung from 20 August 1918; clippings of the Kieler Neueste Nachrichten from June 1914; and clippings from Die Grosse Berliner Illustrietre (date unknown).
- Printed matter, Iceland, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 18: 26)
  Leaflets and newspapers covering battle updates, government food controls, and a published letter from a French surgeon on the battlefield. In Icelandic.
- Programs, entertainment at British G.H.Q., 1919 (Box-folder 18: 27)
  Consists of four programs from concerts and revues put on at British General Headquarters in Montreuil-sur-Mer, France.
- Booklet, "Boi na Fokshanskom napravlenii s 24 iiulia po 1-e avgusta 1917 goda," (Box-folder 19: 1)
- Booklet, "Nashi ranenyye,", undated (Box-folder 19: 2)
  Fold-out booklet featuring illustrations of a wounded soldier's journey from the battlefield to the hospital and his recovery. Includes text in Russian on the backs of the illustrations.
- Booklet, Russian newspaper editorials at the outbreak of the war, undated (Box-folder 19: 3)
  Typed compilation of Russian newspaper editorials from July 1914. Newspapers include Novoie Vremia, Russkia Vikdomosti, Riech, and Russkoie Slovo. In English.
- Calendars, 1918, 1923 (Box-folder 19: 4)
  Two calendars: one page-a-day tear-off calendar from 1918; and one page-a-day tear-off calendar from 1923 with pages starting in December and a photograph of a man glued above it.
- Collected materials, "Istoricheskie materialy o deĭstviiakh VII artilleriiskogo korpusa i 13-oĭ pekhotnoĭ divizii,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 19: 5)
  Imperial military documents. Includes reports of military actions and maps, largely from 1915-1917, with some maps from earlier dates.
- Images, war scenes and officers, undated (Box-folder 19: 6)
  Captioned images (illustrations and reprints of photographs/portraits) of scenes from the battlefield and military officers. Captions are in Russian.
- Military documents, orders, 1917 (Box-folder 19: 7)
  Consists of orders for the Russian army from June to July of 1917.
- Military documents, reports, 1917 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  Consists of reports of various regiments of the Russian army, with accompanying maps, covering the period of June to July of 1917.
- Photographs, family portraits, circa 1916 (Box-folder 19: 9)
  Three studio portraits, presumably of a family: a man in military garb, a seated woman, and a little girl.
- Postcards, undated (Box-folder 19: 10)
  Blank picture postcards produced by Union Postale Universelle, mostly in Russian.
- Postcard, "Karta Europy v litsach v nachale voiny,", 1914 (Box-folder 19: 11)
  Front features colored illustration of Europe with each country as a face/person; back features Russian text as well as a handwritten message.
- War Effort on the United States Home Front, Printed Matter, 1915-1920 (Boxes 19-20)
  Includes materials related to the United War Work Campaign, rationing, and general effects of the war in the United States.
  - Booklet, "The Answer to the Call,", 1918 (Box-folder 19: 12)
    Published by the Jewish Welfare Board as part of the United War Work Campaign.
  - Booklet, "Control and Distribution of Food Supplies,", 1917 (Box-folder 19: 13)
    Text of a 19 June 1917 hearing before the Committee on Agriculture and Forestry, United States Senate, Sixty-Fifth Congress, First Session, relative to S. 2463. The text of the bill, S. 2463, is also included.
  - Booklet, "Every Girl Pulling for Victory,", 1918 (Box-folder 19: 14)
    Booklet encouraging girls to enroll with The Victory Girls and pledge five dollars towards the work of seven organizations (Y.M.C.A., Y.W.C.A., National Catholic War Council - Knights of Columbus, the Jewish Welfare Board, the War Camp Community Service, the American Library Association, and the Salvation Army) as part of the United War Work Campaign.
  - Booklet, "How Boys Can Earn Money,", 1918 (Box-folder 19: 15)
    Booklet encouraging boys to enroll with The Victory Boys and pledge five dollars towards the work of seven organizations (Y.M.C.A., Y.W.C.A., National Catholic War Council - Knights of Columbus, the Jewish Welfare Board, the War Camp Community Service, the American Library Association, and the Salvation Army) as part of the United War Work Campaign.
  - Booklet, "How Uncle Sam's Girl Detectives Help Former Service Men: Some of the Difficult Problems Met and Solved in the Bureau of War Risk Insurance,", circa 1920 (Box-folder 19: 16)
  - Booklet, "Organization of War Transportation Control,", 1918 August (Box-folder 19: 17)
    Published by the Railroad Committee, Chamber of Commerce of the United States. Includes a chart of the organization of the United States Railroad Administration and other war transportation agencies, as well as the function and personnel of each division, section and committee of the Railroad Administration.
  - Booklet, "Report on Activities of the Y.M.C.A. with the A.E.F.,", 1919 May (Box-folder 19: 18)
  - Booklet, "Service Under Fire! The Knights of Columbus,", 1918 (Box-folder 19: 19)
    Published by the National Catholic War Council, Knights of Columbus as part of the United War Work Campaign.
  - Booklet, "State Co-operation in the Efficient National Regulation of Railroads,", 1917 October 27 (Box-folder 19: 20)
    "Information for Employes [sic] and the Public, published by The Pennsylvania Railroad System." Reprint of an address given by Samuel Rea at the annual meeting of the National Association of Railroad Commissioners.
  - Booklet, "This Is the Hut the 'Y' Built!,", 1918 (Box-folder 19: 21)
    Published by the National War Work Council of the Y.M.C.A. as part of the United War Work Campaign.
  - Booklet, "War Service in the home,", 1917 November (Box-folder 19: 22)
    Published by the United States Food Administration.
  - Booklet, "What Your Money Is Doing for Your Boys,", 1918 (Box-folder 19: 23)
    "A Bird's-eye View of the Work of the Y.M.C.A., Y.W.C.A., National Catholic War Council - Knights of Columbus, Jewish Welfare Board, War Camp Community Service, American Library Association, Salvation Army." Published as part of the United War Work Campaign.
  - Correspondence, Famous Author's [sic] Confederation, 1915 February 10 (Box-folder 19: 24)
    Letter to newspaper editor requesting publication of a series of war stories.
  - Correspondence, Service Flag Stamps, circa 1918 (Box-folder 19: 25)
    Form letter from Capital Sales Company advertising Service Flag Stamps and enclosing a sample advertising circular as well as a sample booklet of stamps.
  - Correspondence, United War Work Campaign, 1918 (Box-folder 19: 26)
    Letters to newspaper editors regarding the Campaign and publication of related articles.
  - Flyer, "Shortage of Paper Material - Save Your Waste Paper and Rags,", 1916 (Box-folder 19: 27)
  - Leaflet, "Do You Know Corn Meal? Its Use Means Service to Your Country, Nourishing Food for You,", 1917 (Box-folder 19: 28)
    United States Food Leaflet No. 2, published by the U.S. Department of Agriculture and the U.S. Food Administration.
  - Leaflet, "From the 'Y' for the boys who fight for you,", 1918 (Box-folder 19: 29)
    Published as part of the United War Work Campaign.
  - Leaflet, "How Girls Can Earn Money,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - Leaflet, "The Work of War Camp Community Service,", 1918 (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - Leaflets, food rationing and substitutions, 1918 (Box-folder 20: 3)
    Produced by The Women's Municipal League of Boston, these leaflets offer food substitutions and recipes to assist with the war effort. Topics include "Corn Products," "Oils and Substitute Fats," "Are You Eating Sea Food?," "Preservation of Eggs in Water Glass," "Use These Instead of Cane Sugar," "Cereals," "Meat Substitutes," and "Milk as a Food."
  - Newspaper clipping, New Haven Register, "Save Ice!,", 1919 July 5 (Box-folder 20: 4)
  - Postcard, "What Will Five Dollars Do?,", 1918 (Box-folder 20: 5)
    Informational postcard about the Victory Boys and Victory Girls, published as part of the United War Work Campaign. Back side of the postcard includes "Official Pledge" to be filled out, agreeing to "earn and give" money to the campaign.
  - Poster, "A Girl From This Home Has Enrolled in the Victory Girls to Earn and Give to Make Our Fighters Fit,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 20: 6)
    Published as part of the United War Work Campaign, presumably for display in a window.
  - Poster, Third Liberty Loan Subscriber, 1918 (Box-folder 20: 7)
    Two copies of a poster for Third Liberty Loan subscribers to display in their home windows. Also included is a flyer urging people to hold onto their Liberty Bonds and not sell them.
  - Press release, California Women's Committee of the Councils of National and State Defense, 1918 July 26 (Box-folder 20: 8)
  - Press release, Division of Women's Activities, Department of Justice, 1920 March 19 (Box-folder 20: 9)
    Consists of a series of recipes to be published which advocate the use of less expensive cuts of meat.
  - Press releases, United States Fuel Administration - coal, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 20: 10)
    Cover letters and statements from Albert E. Schwabacher, Federal Fuel Administrator for California, about distribution and use of coal.
  - Press release, United States Fuel Administration - window glass, 1918 March 1 (Box-folder 20: 11)
    An announcement by Albert E. Schwabacher, Federal Fuel Administrator for California, about an order limiting the use of fuel for the production of window glass in the United States. The text of the regulation is also included.
- Recruiting, Registration, and Enlistment in the United States, Printed Matter, 1905-1920 (Boxes 20-21)
  - Booklet, "Detailed Information About the Army, Navy and Marines; Also, Drill Regulations,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 20: 12)
  - Booklet, "Experience of a Recruit in the United States Army,", 1916 (Box-folder 20: 13)
    Written by C.C. Lyon, a reporter for the Columbus, Ohio Citizen, who "joined" the Army in order to learn and write about the training and life of a soldier.
  - Booklet, "Registration Regulations,", 1917 (Box-folder 20: 14)
    Prescribed by the President under authority of the Act of Congress approved May 18, 1917.
  - Booklet, "Sea Training: Join the United States Shipping Board and See the World,", 1919 (Box-folder 20: 15)
    Issued by the United States Shipping Board Recruiting Service, Seattle, Washington.
  - Booklet, "The United States Needs Skilled Engineers in France,", 1918 February 1 (Box-folder 20: 16)
  - Booklet, "United States Service Primer,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 20: 17)
    Book 2, Marine Corps Educational Series. Published by the Marine Corps Publicity Bureau.
  - Booklet, "When He Came Home,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 20: 18)
    Written by Albert Payson Terhune and originally published in T he Saturday Evening Post, the story was reprinted by the Publicity Bureau for the U.S. Army Recruiting Service.
  - Booklet, "Who Am I?,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 20: 19)
    Published by the U.S. Marine Corps.
  - Correspondence, Bureau of Registration, 1917 June (Box-folder 20: 20)
    Two letters, dated June 5 and June 10, 1917, from the State of California Bureau of Registration to county officials, regarding instructions for military registration.
  - Correspondence, Fort Oglethorpe Training Camp, 1917 October 4 (Box-folder 20: 21)
    Letter from the Headquarters of Fort Oglethorpe Training Camp in Georgia to the Chairman for the Local Board, Division 6 in San Francisco, California, informing him that a resident of his district is a member of the Camp, and thus not subject to draft.
  - Correspondence, instructions for registrars, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 20: 22)
    Largely from the County Council of Defense (San Francisco, California), this consists of letters sent to registrars with instructions on completing registration, as well as signs to be posted and examples of forms to be filled out.
  - Correspondence, Post Office Department, 1917, 1919 (Box-folder 20: 23)
    Includes two letters, dated 25 April 1917, to a postmaster, informing him of his duties to assist as a recruiting officer and to report suspicious characters or treasonous acts. With these letters is a form to fill out, Obligation as Recruiting Agent, as well as a copy of the Order of the Postmaster General of 9 April 1917 (which references the Acts of June 3 and August 2, 1916 and the use of the services of postmasters). There is also a follow-up letter requesting that the Obligation, which had not yet been returned, be signed promptly and sent back. In addition, there is an instruction sheet regarding mail for the U.S. Army in Europe (28 July 1917) and a message regarding the acceptance of orders for Army foodstuffs (20 September 1919).
  - Correspondence, Recruiting Service, 1917-1920 (Box-folder 20: 24)
    Consists of correspondence, sent largely by the Army Recruiting Service in San Francisco, to local newspapers requesting that they publish particular stories.
  - Flyer, "Aviation: You May Enlist or Re-enlist,", undated (Box-folder 20: 25)
  - Flyer, "An Excellent Opportunity: Obtain an Appointment to the United States Military Academy,", undated (Box-folder 20: 26)
  - Flyer, "Men Wanted for Quartermaster Corps,", 1917 November 15 (Box-folder 20: 27)
  - Flyer, "U.S. Marine Corps,", undated (Box-folder 20: 28)
    This recruiting flyer urges men to enlist, lists what the training and service will give them, and gives the location of a recruiting service in San Francisco, California.
  - Flyer, "The United States Army as a Career (An Example Worth Following),", 1916 (Box-folder 20: 29)
    Reprint from a San Francisco Examiner article from 23 April 1916.
  - Form, Application for Examination for Commission or Warrant in the United States Naval Reserve Force, 1917 (Box-folder 20: 30)
  - Form, Application to Enlist, 1905-1908 (Box-folder 20: 31)
    Completed applications for joining Company "A" Fifth Infantry, Second Brigade, National Guard of California.
  - Form, Application to Enlist, 1909-1914 (Box-folder 20: 32)
  - Form, Local Board authorizations, undated (Box-folder 20: 33)
    Blank copies of Form 1016-P.M.G.O. (notification that a delinquent individual ordered to report has reported), Form 1022-P.M.G.O. (authorizing an individual's request for transfer of physical examination), and Form 1023-P.M.G.O. (authorizing an individual's request for transfer of classification).
  - Form, Notice of Call and to Appear for Physical Examination, 1917 (Box-folder 20: 34)
    Completed copies of Form No. 103 from the Local Board for Division No. 6 and 9, City of San Francisco, State of California.
  - Form, Notice of Claim and Claim of Appeal by Person Certified to District Board, circa 1917 (Box-folder 20: 35)
    Blank copies of Form No. 151, Notice of Claim of Appeal by Person Certified to District Board and Form No. 153, Claim of Appeal by Person Certified to District Board.
  - Form, Notice of Classification, 1918 (Box-folder 20: 36)
    Two completed copies and one blank copy of Form 1005-P.M.G.O.
  - Form, Order to Report for Military Duty, 1917 (Box-folder 20: 37)
    One completed and one blank copy of Form No. 164 C.
  - Form, Qualification Record, undated (Box-folder 20: 38)
    Two blank copies of this form, No. CCP-1-1000M-9-17, to be filled out with background information about employment, education, and other relevant information.
  - Form, Questionnaire: Claim for Exemption or Deferred Classification, 1917 (Box-folder 20: 39)
    Blank copies of this questionnaire, Form 1001-P.M.G.O. Also included are: a notice urging men to fill out the questionnaire as soon as it is received; P.MG.O. Form 1001-d (Key List of Occupations); and an explanatory memorandum to be inserted in the questionnaire.
  - Form, Registration Cards and Certificates, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 20: 40)
    One completed copy and multiple blank copies of the Registration Card, Form 1, as well as completed Registration Certificates, P.M.G.O Form No. 68.
  - Form, Report of Physical Examination, circa 1917 (Box-folder 20: 41)
    Mostly blank copy of Form 1010-P.M.G.O.; lines for place have been filled in with "Jackson, Cal."
  - Form, Sacramento Bee Ballot on National Military Training, circa 1916 (Box-folder 20: 42)
  - Form, Summarization Blank, 1917 (Box-folder 20: 43)
    Completed forms for Amador County, California, from each of its five Supervisor Districts, plus a form for the entire county. There are also blank copies of the form, as well as one partially filled out copy. It appears the form was used to indicate registration of citizens and declarants from countries with which the United States was not at war, as well as aliens and alien enemies, with columns to indicate specific types of exemptions, non-exemptions, and totals.
  - Leaflet, "Air Service, U.S. Army,", undated (Box-folder 20: 44)
  - Leaflet, "Bulletin" [clarifications to Selective Service Act], 1917 May 24 (Box-folder 20: 45)
    Includes clarifications and corrections to the Selective Service Act of 18 May 1917, issued by the War Department.
  - Leaflet, "Bulletin of Information for Persons Registered,", 1917 (Box-folder 20: 46)
  - Leaflet, "A Letter to the Major General Commandant of the United States Marine Corps from an Ex-Marine,", circa 1914 (Box-folder 20: 47)
    Published by the United States Marine Corps Recruiting Publicity Bureau, this leaflet reprints a 3 June 1914 letter from Joseph S. Eichelberger to Major-General George Barnett, Commandant of the United States Marine Corps praising the Marine Corps and what it did for him.
  - Leaflet, "A Man-o'-Warsman,", 1914 September 1 (Box-folder 20: 48)
    Published by the Publicity Bureau of the United States Navy Recruiting Service.
  - Leaflet, "The Ordnance Department of the United States Army: What It Is, How to Enlist,", undated (Box-folder 20: 49)
  - Leaflet, "Patriotic Americans! Your first duty is to the Constitution…,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 20: 50)
    Leaflet urging Americans to refuse to register for the draft.
  - Leaflet, Selective Service Act, 1917 May (Box-folder 21: 1)
    Text of the act, which authorizes the President to "increase temporarily the Military Establishment of the United States."
  - Leaflet, Service in the Signal Corps, United States Army, 1917 (Box-folder 21: 2)
  - Leaflet, "The Soldier's Opportunity,", circa 1916 (Box-folder 21: 3)
    Originally written for the "Army and Navy News" by Colonel H.O.S. Heistand, then reprinted for use by Army Recruiting.
  - Leaflet, "Special Orders, No. 247,", 1918 October 23 (Box-folder 21: 4)
    Published by Headquarters, Western Department, naming individuals ordered into active service.
  - Leaflet, "Third Series of Training Camps,", 1917 October 1 (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Leaflet, "United States Army Recruiting Circular,", 1915 May 28 (Box-folder 21: 6)
    Circular No. 1, providing instructions to govern recruiting for the Army.
  - Leaflet, "What the Army Did for This Man,", circa 1914 (Box-folder 21: 7)
    Includes a brief biography of Sergeant John J. Fitzgerald, retired, as well as brief descriptions about what the Army is and what it offers, with specific information about the various types of educational and vocational training offered.
  - List, "Men Inducted Into the Service - San Francisco,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 21: 8)
    List of names and addresses of San Francisco, California residents who were inducted into the service. Includes lists for Local Exemption Board Division Number Six, Number Eight, and Number Eleven.
  - List, "Men Ordered to Report to This Local Board for Military Duty,", 1917 November (Box-folder 21: 9)
    Two lists from the Local Board for the County of Amador, California. Each only has the name of one individual ordered to report and be transported to the Mobilization Camp at Camp Lewis, Washington. One list was sent on to the Local Board for Butte County, as the registrant had moved to that jurisdiction.
  - List, "Registration Lists - Amador County,", 1917 June (Box-folder 21: 10)
    List of names of Amador County, California residents who registered for military service on June 5, 1917. Includes lists for Supervisor District Number One (Jackson), Number Four (Sutter Creek), and Number Five (Amador City - though there is a handwritten note indicating that it is also District Number Four).
  - Postcard, War Registration Board, 1917 June 29 (Box-folder 21: 11)
    Postcard from the Headquarters of the War Registration Board in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, inviting men who registered for military service to participate in a parade and reception on 4 July 1917.
  - Poster, "By the President of the United States of America: A Proclamation,", 1918 (Box-folder 21: 12)
    Includes the text of a public resolution, approved by the President on 20 May 1918, regarding military registration. Written in at the top and bottom of the poster is the address of the local registration location.
  - Poster, "Men Wanted for the United States Army,", circa 1916 (Box-folder 21: 13)
    Two versions of the poster: one says "Men Wanted Under 35 Years of Age," and the other says "Men Wanted Between 18 and 35 Years of Age."
  - Poster, "Military Registration, June 5,", 1917 (Box-folder 21: 14)
    In English, Hungarian, French, Russian, Italian, Portuguese, Croatian, Hindi, Greek, Czech, Polish, Romanian, Spanish, German, and Yiddish.
  - Poster, "An Official Appeal to Loyal Americans: Enlist Now, Your President Calls You,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 21: 15)
  - Poster, "Our President's Proclamation and Appeal to All Loyal Americans,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 21: 16)
  - Poster, "Proclamation! Citizens of Sacramento: You are going to enlist!,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 21: 17)
    Urges men to consider the Marines when selecting a branch of the military to enlist it.
  - Poster, "Why Do We Fight Germany?,", 1917 June (Box-folder 21: 18)
    Text of an address by Franklin K. Lane, Secretary of the Interior, given on 4 June 1917 before the Home Club of the Interior Department, Washington, D.C.
  - Poster, "Young Men Wanted for the United States Army,", undated (Box-folder 21: 19)
  - Press releases, United States Army Recruiting News Service, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 21: 20)
    From the San Francisco, California Recruiting District.
  - Press releases, United States Shipping Board, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 21: 21)
  - Rosters, San Francisco men, undated (Box-folder 21: 22)
    Includes rosters (with names, addresses, and occupations) for various companies/units of the army that were made up of men from San Francisco.
  - Typescript, "Air Service Calls for Men,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 21: 23)
  - Typescript, "The Army Offers You...,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 21: 24)
    Numbered list of 25 perks/opportunities.
  - Typescript, "General Recruiting Information,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 21: 25)
    Also includes a list of "21 reasons why a man should enlist."
  - Typescript, "Join the Peace Time Army, Learn a Trade,", undated (Box-folder 21: 26)
  - Typescript, "Notice to Male Citizens and Aliens to Register on June 5th, 1917,", 1917 May 23 (Box-folder 21: 27)
    From the Amador County Council of Defense, in accordance with the Proclamations of the President and of the Governor of California. There is a second copy of the notice in Italian.
  - Typescript, "Policy of the War Department with Reference to the Disposal of Draft Deserters and Delinquents,", circa 1920 (Box-folder 21: 28)
  - Typescript, "Some of the Advantages of an Enlistment in the Army,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 21: 29)